<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ben Dalton</title>
    <link></link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Personal site for Ben Dalton.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 14:56:42 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 14:56:42 -0500</lastBuildDate>

    
      <item>
        <title>The Experiment in Spain</title>
        <link>/experiment-in-spain</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Ben Dalton</author>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NCh3SzePOlo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Alexander Dugin is not Rasputin—he’s another tool in the Kremlin toolbox</title>
        <link>/alexander-dugin</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Ben Dalton</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece originally appeared on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://nyta.us/2017/02/17/alexander-dugin-is-not-rasputin-hes-another-tool-in-the-kremlin-toolbox/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;New York Transatlantic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Ben Dalton&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some of &lt;a href=&quot;https://np.reddit.com/r/politics/comments/5b2p5g/why_vladimir_putins_russia_is_backing_trump/d9lnah7/?context=10000&quot;&gt;the more conspiratorial corners&lt;/a&gt; of the internet, it can sometimes seem that far-right Russian political theorist Alexander Dugin has masterminded, not just Putin’s foreign policy of the last decade, but half the world’s crises. Dugin’s 1997 tome, &lt;i&gt;Foundations of Geopolitics&lt;/i&gt;, is taken as a blueprint for the Kremlin’s latest moves, with Dugin himself—complete with flowing Orthodox beard—cast as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/2016/07/25/487380876/a-look-at-donald-trumps-ties-to-russia&quot;&gt;Rasputin&lt;/a&gt;-esque whisperer behind the throne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t buy it. Dugin is no oracle of Russian policy. He’s the tool of a cynical and opportunistic regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be sure, Dugin has a penchant for predicting the future. In &lt;i&gt;Foundations of Geopolitics&lt;/i&gt;, he declared that Ukraine makes no sense as a state and called for the eastern part of the country to be brought under Moscow’s control. He even correctly predicted the design of the separatist Donetsk Republic’s flag “two months before a contest was held to decide it,” according to Charles Clover in &lt;i&gt;Black Wind, White Snow&lt;/i&gt;, a history of Russian nationalism published last year. &lt;i&gt;Foundations&lt;/i&gt; also seems to anticipate last year’s Brexit vote, advising that the United Kingdom should be isolated from continental Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dugin also has a knack for turning up at the center of Russian conflicts. Two years ago, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/alexander-dugin-russian-academic-linking-us-president-donald-trump-vladimir-putin-turkey-president-a7560611.html&quot;&gt;he was apparently instrumental&lt;/a&gt; in de-escalating tensions between Moscow and Ankara after Turkey shot down a Russian jet. In 2008, he appeared in South Ossetia in the weeks before Russian and Georgian forces clashed over the breakaway enclave. Dugin is popular among the security types and propagandists who orbit Vladimir Putin. In fact, he spent years lecturing Russia’s future military leaders at the prestigious Academy of the General Staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, for all Dugin seems to keep a thumb on the pulse of Kremlin policymaking, it would be a mistake to view him as the architect of Putin’s revanchist, nationalist Russia. &lt;a href=&quot;http://jordanrussiacenter.org/news/american-fascism-lessons-russia/&quot;&gt;Unlike certain other would-be authoritarians&lt;/a&gt;, Putin coopts and controls his ideologues, alternately sponsoring and abandoning them according to the needs of the moment. While the Kremlin has lately cast itself as conservative defender of “Western Civilization,” its tactics at home and abroad are opportunistic, cynical and ideologically agnostic. Instead, what never wavers is its commitment to maintaining the current, highly profitable regime, with Putin at the top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While alleged Russian intervention on behalf of Donald Trump’s “outsider” campaign has generated headlines, the Kremlin has extended support to leftwing critics of the Washington establishment, too. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2017/01/13/how-putin-played-the-far-left.html&quot;&gt;As journalist Casey Michel has reported&lt;/a&gt;, Moscow courted Green Party candidate Jill Stein at the 2015 gala also attended by ousted Trump National Security Adviser Michael Flynn. Russia’s English-language broadcaster RT goes out of its way to air dissenting voices, including lefty activists and commentators who rarely if ever appear on CNN, MSNBC or Fox. As a rule, if you’ve got something critical to say about the US-backed “globalist” order, then RT would be glad to offer you a platform.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ideological opportunism mirrors how Putin’s government has long sought to coopt its domestic opposition. In the ‘aughts, citing the lack of a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/aug/17/russia.tomparfitt&quot;&gt;major alternative party&lt;/a&gt;,” the Kremlin merged several small parties into a single, government-approved opposition. British writer Peter Pomerantsev has written how, for years, the Kremlin would sponsor both humans rights and nationalist groups, modern art exhibits and Orthodox demonstrations. After mass street protests rattled the regime in 2011–12, the Kremlin shifted toward more overt repression, but still harnesses the power of far-right nationalist groups that might otherwise prove a threat to the ruling elite. Moreover, these nationalist narratives help to legitimate the regime, which is where Dugin comes in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dugin’s own seesawing fortune reflects the Kremlin’s essential ambivalence toward his kind. Dugin’s star rises whenever relations between Russia and the West deteriorate and falls during periods of rapprochement. For example, he enjoyed his own talk show on Russian Radio until the Obama-era “reset” in U.S.–Russia relations, when he was fired. In 2014, Moscow State University removed him from his post as head of the sociology department, a move Dugin attributed to his “&lt;a href=&quot;https://warisboring.com/putins-mad-philosopher-sacked-from-top-post-38c6d14b3a2#.3dbhnkwoy&quot;&gt;hard-line support for the separatists in Ukraine&lt;/a&gt;.” At the time, the Kremlin was seen to be shifting away from outright annexation of Ukraine’s separatist territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far from “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/russia-fsu/2014-03-31/putins-brain&quot;&gt;Putin’s brain&lt;/a&gt;” or “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2014/04/02/alexander-dugin-the-crazy-ideologue-of-the-new-russian-empire.html&quot;&gt;the crazy ideologue of the new Russian empire&lt;/a&gt;,” Dugin is just another tool in the Kremlin’s ideological toolbox. He and other ultranationalists undoubtedly have influence—but only as much as the Kremlin permits them. In the end, Putin’s coterie has no ideology other than its own preservation and enrichment. Looking to Dugin’s brand of blood and soil nationalism to predict Moscow’s next move would be a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Crony Capitalism? How About Crony Socialism?</title>
        <link>/crony-socialism</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Ben Dalton</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece originally appeared on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://nyta.us/2017/02/02/crony-capitalism-how-about-crony-socialism/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;New York Transatlantic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Ben Dalton&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common story that Americans tell themselves about the collapse of the Soviet Union goes like this: upon entering office, Ronald Reagan boosted US military spending, forcing the USSR to spend more, too. In time, Soviet budget deficits compounded other economic mismanagement and culminated in the Union’s disintegration in late 1991. At some point, Reagan also urged Soviet General Secretary Mikhail Gorbachev to remove a symbolic wall, and Gorbachev, perhaps stirred by the president’s soaring rhetoric, complied. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another explanation—and one with more evidence behind it—holds that the USSR was a victim of the late ‘80s oil glut. Falling oil and gas prices gutted Soviet exports, crippling the economy and leading to collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his new book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Struggle-Save-Soviet-Economy-Gorbachev/dp/1469630176&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Struggle to Save the Soviet Economy: Mikhail Gorbachev and the Collapse of the USSR&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Chris Miller argues that neither account gets the Soviet economic crisis right. Neither Reagan nor oil, but domestic politics and powerful interest groups brought down the Soviet Union, Miller said during &lt;a href=&quot;http://harriman.columbia.edu/event/book-talk-struggle-save-soviet-economy-mikhail-gorbachev-and-collapse-ussr-chris-miller&quot;&gt;a talk&lt;/a&gt; at Columbia University’s Harriman Institute on Wednesday, Feb. 1. Miller is associate director of the Brady-Johnson Program in Grand Strategy at Yale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the mid-80s, the Soviet economy was stagnant but not in crisis, Miller said. Growth had slowed, but budget deficits were small. Gorbachev sought to kickstart the economy by implementing a series of market reforms, many borrowed from China, which with its high growth and familiar institutions offered the Soviets an attractive model. These reforms came to be known as &lt;i&gt;perestroika&lt;/i&gt;, or “restructuring.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among other liberalizing measures, China’s Deng Xiaoping had permitted firms to sell surplus production and, with “household-responsibility” agriculture, essentially de-collectivized the farms. The result was booming GDP growth throughout the 1980s, which Gorbachev wanted to replicate. Moreover, since the Chinese Communist Party had modeled many state institutions on the USSR of the 1950s, Deng’s reforms seemed like a good fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Deng, however, Gorbachev encountered stiff resistance from Party insiders. The Soviet economy was dominated by massive, state-owned military, energy and agricultural complexes—this last representing “the triumph of socialism in the countryside.” High-level officials in the Politburo and other Soviet institutions condemned Gorbachev’s reforms for opening the door to capitalism, but then followed their critiques with appeals for more funding for pet industries. Again and again, Miller found in the notes of Politburo meetings this ideological opposition paired with requests for money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Miller, Gorbachev was only able to proceed with &lt;i&gt;perestroika&lt;/i&gt; by striking a bargain. In exchange for Chinese-style reforms, he agreed to invest in industries on whose behalf top officials had been lobbying. Soviet agricultural subsidies, already huge, grew even larger. Surplus goods piled up in warehouses. And the country’s budget deficit began to balloon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After international loans dried up, Gorbachev financed the deficit by printing money. At the same time, he refused to increase prices for fear of provoking mass unrest and alienating his remaining bases of support. Production ground to a halt as firms received ever less valuable rubles for their goods. By 1991, the USSR’s deficit was 30 percent of GDP and its economy was near paralysis. When Yeltsin agreed with the leaders of Ukraine and Belarus to dissolve the Union, Gorbachev was powerless to stop it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miller acknowledged that Reagan’s arms buildup and the late-80s oil shock may have destabilized the USSR. But he argued that neither was sufficient on its own to cause Soviet collapse. He pointed to export earnings, comprised almost entirely of oil and gas sales, which dropped from approximately eight to five percent of GDP between 1985 and 1990. While significant, that decline was not decisive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, according to Miller, Gorbachev was weak, while the Soviet Union’s interest groups were strong. In fact, Gorbachev may have pushed democratization as a means of eroding the strength of the interests opposing his reforms. If so, political liberalization took place too slowly to grant Gorbachev the power he needed to override those interests and close the deficit. Where Stalin had made the system work through terror—killing or shuffling top brass before they could become entrenched and therefore threats—Gorbachev was forced to navigate a landscape of powerful opponents. In other words, it was crony socialism, not hostile capitalism, that made sustainable reform of the Soviet Union impossible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>World Learning Celebrates the 2016 Advancing Leaders Fellows</title>
        <link>/world-learning-celebrates-the-2016-advancing-leaders-fellows</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Ben Dalton</author>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WWSdwzMj4wc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>With Surging Membership, DSA Braces for President Trump</title>
        <link>/with-surging-membership-dsa-braces-for-president-trump</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Ben Dalton</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece originally appeared on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dsausa.org/_with_surging_membership_dsa_braces_for_president_trump&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;dsausa.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Ben Dalton&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After immigrating from China, Lynn Wang’s parents lived in the United States for three decades without encountering discrimination or racial abuse, until the final months of the 2016 presidential campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My mom was leaving yoga, and a woman from our hometown just pulled up next to her, leaned out of her car and started calling her racial slurs,” said Wang, a student at the University of Southern California. “We’ve been in Manhattan Beach for decades and never had that kind of thing happen before.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A desire to fight what she describes as the “toxic atmosphere” surrounding Donald Trump’s presidential campaign and victory is partly what drove Wang to join the Democratic Socialists of America (DSA), the country’s largest democratic-socialist organization. A veteran of the Bernie Sanders campaign, Wang learned of DSA from a fellow volunteer. As a member, she plans to organize on behalf of those “who feel particularly threatened by Trump’s rhetoric.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m afraid that bigotry won at the polls, and people think that bigotry has a place in the streets,” Wang said. “I hope that we will be able to take a part in the resistance against the Trump administration.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wang is among thousands of new recruits to have joined DSA in recent months, a “Trump bump” that has boosted progressive organizations across the United States. In the first six days after Trump’s victory, DSA signed up over 1,600 dues-paying, online members, an 18 percent increase in membership, according to David Duhalde, the organization’s deputy director. Even before Trump’s election, Duhalde says that DSA had grown in prominence thanks to Bernie Sanders, a self-described democratic socialist whose presidential campaign DSA supported. Facing a Trump administration, DSA and other socialist groups offer members a channel for organized resistance that goes beyond electoral politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As a national organization with chapters in red states and blue states, in rural, suburban and urban communities we feel that we’re uniquely positioned to really build a national network and community of people that can confront this kind of rhetoric,” said Maria Svart, DSA national director. “We’re going to resist every bad thing they try to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On election night, Chris Maisano caught a cab to Brooklyn with several other DSA members as the first results began to trickle in. Their plan for the night was to watch what they assumed would be a Hillary Clinton victory at a live broadcast of the leftist Chapo Trap House podcast. By the time he reached the event, Maisano realized that Trump had a real shot at winning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The mood quickly switched from slightly optimistic nervousness to just increasing demoralization and dread,” Maisano said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. socialists dislike Clinton, whom they consider to represent the neoliberal, anti-labor wing of the Democratic Party, but most nonetheless strongly preferred her to Trump. Now that Trump will be president, their list of worries is long. Foremost for many is the possibility that the Trump administration will follow through on the president-elect’s campaign rhetoric and target vulnerable communities such as immigrants, Muslims and LGBT Americans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The first immediate threat is that he has the Obama deportation machine,” Duhalde said. “I understand when radicals are like, ‘well, Obama’s already deporting people,’ but I think Trump will use it much more cruelly.” Duhalde pointed out that Trump will inherit lists of undocumented immigrants who are temporarily protected from deportation by Obama’s Deferred Action for Childhood Arrivals (DACA) policy. The Trump administration could target those on the DACA registry, Duhalde said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another concern is that the Trump administration, together with the Republican-controlled Congress, will continue long-standing GOP efforts to undermine organized labor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Republican Party has an opportunity to really go after the labor movement, what remains of it,” said Maisano. “They’re going to go after the [National Labor Relations Board]. They’re going to try to repeal many of the regulations about overtime and wages that the Obama administration put in place. It seems pretty clear that at some point they’re going to push to pass a national right to work law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Svart said that defending unions will be a priority for DSA under a Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For all of the flaws of the leaders of most of the labor movement, we have to protect unions,” she said. “They are uniquely positioned, and over history have done more than anyone else, to build a multiracial movement of working class people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official topic at the first Brooklyn Jacobin reading group held after the election was socialist politics in Brazil, but the conversation kept returning to Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think you should be in the first line against Trump,” said Pedro Fuentes, a visiting speaker and official in Brazil’s Socialism and Liberty Party (PSOL). Around the room heads nodded. “Anti-Trump. This is the first task you have.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Trump’s election, left-wing groups have strategized how best to respond to his coming administration and Republican control of both the executive and legislative branches of government. One immediate reaction has been to organize and join protests against Trump’s victory, as well as offer solidarity and support to groups that have been targeted since the election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Svart said that DSA held an emergency conference call urging local chapters to join hands with community organizations – religious institutions, other activists, clinics – that support vulnerable populations. Together with these groups, DSA seeks to create sanctuaries from the rash of hate crimes and harassment that has followed Trump’s win, Svart said. She believes that coordination with other groups will be necessary under a Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re also working with our DSA groups to have emergency meetings to talk about the new political terrain and publicly protest in several ways, one of which is actually in the streets, registering discontent with the election results,” said Svart. “We’re also having folks write letters to the editor, write opinion editorials, call into radio shows, and things like that, so we’re providing talking points.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One question is whether socialists should attempt to pull the Democratic Party to the left by supporting its progressive wing, represented by figures such as Keith Ellison, the Minnesota representative seeking to become chair of the Democratic National Committee. Svart said she is open to serving as a kind of “Tea Party of the left” that backs progressive Democrats against centrists in primaries, as well as running independent candidates where they stand a chance of winning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We believe in both working with what we have and at the same time being independent and building an alternative,” Svart said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, many activists are skeptical that the Democrats can be transformed into a genuine, national party of the left, in large part because the party’s centrist wing remains so influential. Socialist critics contend that the party’s national leadership is isolated from its base and slow to respond to grassroots concerns. Longtime party leaders are not likely to cede control to reenergized progressives without a fight, activists said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These faction fights are fascinating because I don’t feel that one side can truly dominate the other,” Duhalde said. “The important thing is for the progressives just to keep challenging and not give up.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the election, DSA members have organized and joined protests against Trump, a form of direct action that Duhalde said will be important given how little leverage the left will wield in a Republican-dominated government. The organization plans to protest Trump’s inauguration this January in Washington, DC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite opposing Trump’s rhetoric and policies, DSA members cautioned against demonizing his voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think the wrong narrative to take away [from this election] would be that half of our population is stupid, racist, bigoted and ignorant,” Wang said. “I think that the greatest failure of the liberal left so far has been that they’ve failed to come up with a counter-narrative to Trump’s rhetoric.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Maisano, only the left can provide an effective alternative to Trumpism, one that speaks to the millions who sat out the election or even voted for Trump because they felt that conventional politicians had forgotten them. Activists will need to find the right balance between defending against a hostile Trump administration and building a viable alternative, Maisano said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Liberalism is not going to protect us against this,” he said. “They’re not going to offer an alternative.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even with the damage he believes the Trump administration will do, Maisano said that the future of U.S. politics belongs to the social democratic constituency that emerged during the 2015-16 campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is still far too early to tell how all of this will play out, but despite my fears about what a Trump administration will bring in the short term, I am optimistic that the most dynamic and emergent forces in U.S. politics today are on our side,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Forced Fashion</title>
        <link>/forced-fashion</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <author>Ben Dalton</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece originally appeared on &lt;a href=&quot;http://thediplomat.com/2016/11/forced-fashion-made-in-the-usa-with-uzbek-cotton/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Diplomat&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Ben Dalton&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NEW YORK — Inside American Apparel&amp;rsquo;s brightly lit location in Greenwich Village, 20-somethings pick through the company&amp;rsquo;s signature clean-cut offerings, flanked by stylized Greek columns. Labels on the clothes read &amp;ldquo;Made in USA with US and imported components&amp;rdquo; – the company&amp;rsquo;s vertically integrated model, with clothes manufactured in Southern California, distinguishes American Apparel from most other large fashion retailers. Online, the company declares its commitment to sustainability, offering an &amp;ldquo;Organic Line&amp;rdquo; produced from &amp;ldquo;100% USDA Certified Organic and pesticide-free cotton.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, American Apparel is also one of the last major U.S. fashion retailers to refuse to sign a pledge to avoid knowingly sourcing cotton from Uzbekistan, which employs widespread forced labor in cotton production. Another prominent holdout, Forever 21, announced that it would sign the pledge while reporting this story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with Polo Ralph Lauren and a handful of other retailers, American Apparel has ignored calls to join hundreds of other companies in signing &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://www.sourcingnetwork.org/the-cotton-pledge&quot;&gt;the Cotton Pledge&lt;/a&gt;, which commits companies &amp;ldquo;to not knowingly source Uzbek cotton for the manufacturing of any of our products until the Government of Uzbekistan ends the practice of forced child and adult labor in its cotton sector.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For activists, the silence is frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I would love to have them sign on. I think it&amp;rsquo;s a travesty that they haven&amp;rsquo;t,&amp;rdquo; said Patricia Jurewicz, founder and director of the Responsible Sourcing Network (RSN), which created and administers the Cotton Pledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other organizations go even further. Continuing to purchase Uzbek cotton &amp;ldquo;is an endorsement of state-sponsored slavery,&amp;rdquo; said Sarah Newell, campaigns associate at the Cotton Campaign, a coalition of human rights, labor and business organizations dedicated to ending forced labor in Uzbekistan. &amp;ldquo;Every company has an absolute responsibility to take action and boycott Uzbek cotton until the government ceases to mobilize their citizens against their will.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RSN issued its Cotton Pledge in 2011, beginning with companies that had already committed not to source cotton from Uzbekistan. Today, over 200 companies have joined the effort, including giants such as Wal-Mart, Target and Disney.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participating retailers cite their commitment to human rights as the deciding factor. One of the last holdouts, Forever 21, agreed to sign the pledge this October. &amp;ldquo;Forever 21 shares the same goals of eliminating child and adult forced labor, and we are fully aligned with the spirit and purpose of Responsible Sourcing Network&amp;rsquo;s cotton pledge,&amp;rdquo; the company said in an email statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American Apparel and Polo Ralph Lauren did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cotton in Uzbekistan is big business. In 2015-16, the country was the world&amp;rsquo;s sixth largest producer of cotton, &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://usda.mannlib.cornell.edu/usda/fas/cotton-market//2010s/2016/cotton-market-09-12-2016.pdf&quot;&gt;according to the U.S. Department of Agriculture&lt;/a&gt;. The five countries that produced more all have populations much larger than Uzbekistan&amp;rsquo;s 30 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uzbekistan&amp;rsquo;s government controls every aspect of the cotton industry, imposing quotas on cotton farmers, setting prices and marshaling a workforce of over 1 million citizens each harvest season. Unable to attract workers at the artificially low wage set by the government, officials threaten citizens with &amp;ldquo;loss of land, confiscation of property, criminal charges, civil fines, and verbal and physical abuse,&amp;rdquo; according to &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://laborrights.org/sites/default/files/publications/Financing_Forced_Labor_1.pdf&quot;&gt;a September 2016 report&lt;/a&gt; from the International Labor Rights Forum (ILRF). Many workers are pulled from their professions as doctors, teachers or civil servants, leaving gaps in vital services during the weeks of the harvest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Yesterday, it was published… that one newborn died in the hospital,&amp;rdquo; said Alisher Ilkhamov, a research associate at SOAS, University of London, and program officer at Open Society Foundations. &amp;ldquo;The young mother, she didn&amp;rsquo;t receive treatment and attention from doctors because they were absent. They were all in the cotton fields.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The campaign to end forced labor in Uzbekistan claims some successes, such as the government acting to ensure that young children are not forced into the cotton fields. However, officials have compensated by replacing child workers with adults, according to &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://www.ilo.org/wcmsp5/groups/public/---ed_norm/---ipec/documents/publication/wcms_427620.pdf&quot;&gt;a 2015 report &lt;/a&gt;from the International Labour Organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After buying cotton from farmers at artificially low prices, the government exports thousands of metric tons to foreign buyers. Revenues &amp;ldquo;disappear into a fund controlled by senior officials which is neither reported to the public nor the national assembly,&amp;rdquo; according to the ILRF. The system is a holdover from the Soviet era, when the government raised export revenues by forcing children, students and civil servants to pick cotton during the harvest season, Ilkhamov said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This top-to-bottom state control of the cotton industry is why U.S. activists feel a boycott is appropriate. Jurewicz noted that in other industries her aim is to encourage ethically sourced trade, not shut it down entirely. Uzbekistan is a unique case, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;All the cotton in Uzbekistan is harvested under a corrupt and exploitative system, so it makes sense to boycott because it will put pressure on the government that they have to change,&amp;rdquo; Jurewicz said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the largest buyers of Uzbek cotton are Bangladeshi traders and companies, said Matthew Fischer-Daly, a student at Cornell University. Until August, Fischer-Daly was the campaign coordinator at the Cotton Campaign. These companies then spin the cotton into yarn, weave fabrics and manufacture the actual garments which &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424127887323998604578567522527553976&quot;&gt;brands like Polo Ralph Lauren sell in their stores&lt;/a&gt;. American Apparel is unusual in that it controls more links in the manufacturing chain. Most retailers are many steps removed from their raw materials – and that is a problem for companies attempting to avoid Uzbek cotton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Many companies, even those that have signed the pledge, continue to manage their supply chain without actually knowing where their cotton comes from,&amp;rdquo; Fischer-Daly said. Cotton from Uzbekistan goes &amp;ldquo;to a spinning factory, where it&amp;rsquo;s often mixed with cotton bales from many other places…That spinning factory is still several tiers down from the U.S. retailer.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, even U.S. companies that conduct audits of their suppliers may not be able to guarantee that their cotton did not originate from Uzbekistan. That&amp;rsquo;s why the Cotton Pledge states that companies would not &amp;ldquo;knowingly&amp;rdquo; source Uzbek cotton, which Jurewicz said was a strategic decision. She considers signing the Cotton Pledge a &amp;ldquo;first step,&amp;rdquo; with rigorous tracking and verification to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you can&amp;rsquo;t even take that very first step, what&amp;rsquo;s likely happening is that your suppliers are using Uzbek cotton,&amp;rdquo; Jurewicz said. &amp;ldquo;They are propping up a government that exploits its own people, putting money into the pockets of the rich and the elite, and minimizing the future of Uzbek citizens.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Malawi Scholarship Program</title>
        <link>/the-malawi-scholarship-program</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <author>Ben Dalton</author>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XCRICEDDhR0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleague Kathryn Schoenberger and I traveled to Malawi in April 2016 to document the work of the Malawi Scholarship Program, a USAID-funded and World Learning-run program that trains health care workers throughout Malawi in everything from community midwifery to nutritional science to traditional nursing. This video tells the story of the program in four profiles.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mandela Washington Fellows Alumni TIES - Nairobi, Kenya</title>
        <link>/mandela-washington-fellows-alumni-ties</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <author>Ben Dalton</author>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aXyyB2mKWRs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tethered Narratives</title>
        <link>/tethered-narratives</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <author>Ben Dalton</author>
        <description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://tetherednarratives.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../public/images/tethered-narratives.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toward the end of 2015, I made &lt;a href=&quot;http://benjamindalton.com/public/interactives/world-learning-annual-report-2015/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a prototype digital annual report&lt;/a&gt; for World Learning, based on the design of the print version/PDF that had already been assembled. The idea wasn&#39;t to replace the original, but to experiment and see what might be possible in the future. Other than a few stubborn bugs (misaligned images here and there), I was happy with the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This spring, Alison offered me the chance to make a web version of the literary journal she was creating with her Literature of Immigration students at Stony Brook University. At first, I planned to use the annual report as a template, but switched to a WordPress theme at Alison’s suggestion. Her recommendation was the right call, since &lt;a href=&quot;http://tetherednarratives.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the finished product&lt;/a&gt; turned out nicely. I made only slight modifications to the SimpleMag theme, which handled the heavy lifting and freed me to focus on design and presentation. I set up the site on a DigitalOcean droplet, then transferred it to a permanent DigitalOcean account that Stony Brook controls. As long as a client is comfortable using DigitalOcean as their host, this seems like an easy way to deliver a project.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kosovo Newborn</title>
        <link>/kosovo-newborn</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <author>Ben Dalton</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/interactives/kosovo-newborn/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/kosovo-newborn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The University of Prishtina campus&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In March, I traveled to World Learning&amp;#39;s Kosovo office for a few days of filming. In April, I attended Bocoup&amp;#39;s OpenVis Conference in Boston and got (re)inspired to play around with HTML5 background video. Combine those two influences, and &lt;a href=&quot;/public/interactives/kosovo-newborn/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is the result. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used reveal.js for the slide effect. With this much video, loading speed is a concern. The development branch of reveal.js supports lazy loading media assets. The current production branch does not. By the time I realized this, I had modified the latter too much to switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next few weeks, I will be working on a similar project using someone else&amp;#39;s footage from Mexico. If I have the time, the next one will be IE-compatible. Also, each video slide will play its own audio when selected, rather than a single track of Prishtina-footballer-cum-Gregorian chanting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    

  </channel>
</rss>
